<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Moodle | Kate Pyper</title>
    <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/tag/moodle/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kate-pyper.github.io/tag/moodle/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Moodle</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kate-pyper.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Moodle</title>
      <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/tag/moodle/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Initial Step Towards a Blended Classroom</title>
      <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/first-step-to-blended/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/first-step-to-blended/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first ever blog post. I decided to start a blog to give me a place to write down some thoughts on my teaching, particularly as we head into a unique year thanks to Covid!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m doing a PGCert in learning and teaching in higher education and have now taken 40 credits worth of classes. I&amp;rsquo;m really interested in the different teaching and learning pedagogies and wanted to try something totally new. Specifically I&amp;rsquo;m keen to implement blended learning in my classes, which isn&amp;rsquo;t currently the norm in my department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I&amp;rsquo;ve learned anything from my PGCert so far it&amp;rsquo;s that reflecting on teaching practice is really important. For context, I&amp;rsquo;ve taken over a class for the next academic year that has been in its current state since its creation (around 10 years ago I think) and I&amp;rsquo;m keen to make some fairly big changes to it. I&amp;rsquo;m definitely expecting some challenges to pop up along the way and wanted to have a dedicated space to keep track of the changes that I&amp;rsquo;ve made, along with my successes and failures. If anyone happens to come across this and have a bit of discussion around anything then that&amp;rsquo;s definitely a bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class that I&amp;rsquo;m focussing on (for now) is a 20 credit module that is delivered to students across three different MSc programmes. The students come from a wide range of backgrounds, so we have to assume no prior knowledge of programming or statistics. We assume a base level of high-school level maths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course itself combines an introduction to programming in R with introductory linear regression. Each of these topics sits within its own five week block. When delivered face-to-face there are 6 hours of live content per week split between lectures and practical sessions. In the first 5 weeks this is 2 hours of lectures and 4 hours of tutorials, for the second half the split of lectures to practicals is 4 hours to 2. The first thing that I am planning on doing is making this more consistent throughout the class, following the structure in the first half to make the focus of the class more practical. This change is also in line with the learning objective of the class, which focus more on the students being able to complete a full analysis (although of course the theoretical components will still be there!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class will be based in Strathclyde&amp;rsquo;s VLE, MyPlace, which is a wrapper for Moodle. So most (but not all) of the things that I discuss here will relate to Moodle as well as MyPlace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-structure&#34;&gt;General structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the course, each week will consist of two topics. The main learning materials that would be covered in lectures will be split into sensible small chunks, and each chunk will build on the previous chunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These chunks will have some reading or video content to give students information, and will be associated with at least one exercise or quiz for feedback to provide deeper understanding. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.moodle.org/39/en/Lesson_activity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The lesson module&lt;/a&gt; in Moodle is an underrated feature that lends itself well to this, and external tools can be easily embedded into individual pages within the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to pull materials from a variety of sources, including some that I&amp;rsquo;ve developed myself. I still have to work on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tutorials&#34;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing that I have thought a lot about recently is how to deliver a typical computer lab or tutorial remotely. I think that, given that the students haven&amp;rsquo;t signed up to an online education, it is really important to still have synchronous sessions where students can interact with lecturers and tutors. Also important since it&amp;rsquo;s one of my favourite parts of teaching!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue with this is that not all students are comfortable with this, and some students may not even be able to access these session due to poor connectivity or limited technology. From my perspective then, it is important to think about a variety of options to provide tutorial support. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided on three main ways that I will provide tutorial support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Live tutorial session&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will function in effectively the same way as a regular tutorial, but will use Zoom instead of being in a computer lab. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on having multiple tutors (the exact number will be dictated by the class size) and splitting the students into breakout groups to encourage collaboration. The students will be given the opportunity to self-select their group prior to the semester starting. I&amp;rsquo;ll then make any adjustments to produce properly sized groups, and get feedback from students who are unable to attend these live sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tutorial sheets will be available, along with the other materials, the week prior (i.e. week 2 materials will be made available at the beginning of week 1) as is typical in our fully online classes. The only thing I can&amp;rsquo;t decide on is whether it is best to have a really structured session or a completely unstractured session. I can see pros and cons of both. At the moment I&amp;rsquo;m leaning towards an unstructured session (as in a computer lab), where the tutors and I will drop in to tutorial groups almost in the same way as walking around a tutorial and talking to students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solutions for each tutorial sheet will be made available after the corresponding live session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Live &amp;ldquo;Office Hours&amp;rdquo; session&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second option for tutorial support is to attend a live drop-in session. I&amp;rsquo;ll sit on an open Zoom session for an hour and answer any questions from students who drop in. The idea is that dropping in to ask a question will require less data (and less bandwidth) than a full live session, but still provides personal contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sessions will be completely unstructured, and will require students to do the work and ask specific questions. The nice thing about this is that it allows screen sharing which makes it fairly straightforward to diagnose programming issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Discussion forum/email&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final way in which I will offer support is via a discussion forum. I haven&amp;rsquo;t had great success with these in the past, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to label these &amp;ldquo;Q&amp;amp;A&amp;rdquo; so that they have a definite purpose and students aren&amp;rsquo;t going to be put off by the word &amp;ldquo;discussion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If students still feel uncomfortable posting then I will answer questions via e-mail, and also add any relevant questions to the discussion forum with an answer. Similarly, if any common questions come up in the live tutorial or during the office hour session these will be added to the Q&amp;amp;A thread with an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m anticipating that the forums will be populated by me for at least the first couple of weeks, but I&amp;rsquo;ll encourage students to look to these for answers and am hoping that seeing some questions that have already been asked will give students the confidence to post their own questions. These will then become a useful study tool, since they will essentially act as a &amp;ldquo;FAQ&amp;rdquo; for each week.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
