<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Teaching | Kate Pyper</title>
    <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/tag/teaching/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kate-pyper.github.io/tag/teaching/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Teaching</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kate-pyper.github.io/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Teaching</title>
      <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/tag/teaching/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s Nearly Showtime</title>
      <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/nearly-showtime/nearly-showtime/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/nearly-showtime/nearly-showtime/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve just entered week 0 (the induction week) of the semester here at Strathclyde, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been working more than usual trying to get good quality content online for the upcoming semester. The first two weeks&amp;rsquo; worth of material is ready to go but there&amp;rsquo;s still 8 weeks left to do - I&amp;rsquo;m definitely not kidding myself that this semester is going to be straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is going to be a reasonably short post, but i&amp;rsquo;m going to pin point some things that I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing over the past few weeks (some of which to help the students and some because I&amp;rsquo;m a perfectionist and can&amp;rsquo;t help myself).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;making-materials-for-offline-as-well-as-online&#34;&gt;Making materials for offline as well as online&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent quite a lot of time making text resources because these transfer a bit easier to students with limited internet access, and some things are just easier to explain in text than in a video. I&amp;rsquo;ve used R-markdown to create this text content, because it allows me to create both html and pdf documents. I&amp;rsquo;ve structured my course so that each small topic comes with text online, generally with some exercises, and then has an associated downloadable pdf document that contains all of the information from the online activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the online text contains embedded exercises. I want to encourage the students to work through these. I&amp;rsquo;ve done this firstly by setting activity completion on the online materials but not on the downloadable materials; and secondly by restricting access to the downloadable materials until the online activity has been attempted (though if a student were unable to access the online activity I would provide access to the PDF document). The image below shows this for one of my activities in week 3.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/Activity_completion.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/Activity_completion.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;consistent-but-not-consistent&#34;&gt;Consistent but not consistent&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to keep a fairly consistent weekly structure, with each week being visually similar to each other. Each week starts with a description of the learning objectives, followed by the materials and links to the live zoom sessions that are available each week (see below).&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/LO_general.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/LO_general.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The end of the week is also pretty consistent, and consists of the student reflection exercise discussed 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/student-reflection-for-feedback/&#34;&gt;in one of my previous posts&lt;/a&gt;, as well as a weekly formative assessment in the form of either a quiz or a submission as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/summary_materials.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/summary_materials.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the week the students will work through a number of activities (I&amp;rsquo;m aiming for somewhere between 6 and 10). Those which contain a lot of information are contained in lessons and those which contain smaller (but no less important) points are contained within pages as demonstrated below.&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/Activities.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/Activities.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within these activities I have tried to give a bit of variety. There are large elements of text and examples, which are interspersed with the occasional video where I think these are useful. These will also contain some sort of associated activity, be that an online programming activity, or an interactive H5P activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall the goal is to be consistent, though not so consistent that the students get bored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;formatting&#34;&gt;Formatting&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something that I&amp;rsquo;ve found myself enjoying quite a bit recently (and something that I&amp;rsquo;ve become a bit obsessive about) is formatting my materials nicely in MyPlace/Moodle. As I mentioned, I have been using R-markdown to produce HTML materials. I then use the output from that and copy it into the html editor within MyPlace - this is a bit hidden you need to click on the button for more options and then click on the button with &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; shown on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to not about this is that MyPlace has been created so that it is difficult to tamper with the themes, which means that it is hit-or-miss whether CSS will work. So I&amp;rsquo;ve had to do the formatting old school and use the style attribute of various HTML tags. I&amp;rsquo;ve saved the commonly used styles into a text document to make this a bit easier. I have styles for the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Code and output blocks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/code_output.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/code_output.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;blockquotes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/blockquote.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/blockquote.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Information/Instruction Boxes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/infobox.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/infobox.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have also elected to change the default inline code colour for better accessibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;video-editing&#34;&gt;Video Editing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final thing that I have been doing over the past few weeks is editing video. I&amp;rsquo;ve used zoom to record since it&amp;rsquo;s easy to get a video of both your face and a shared screen (be that slides or R). You can download a video that contains the shared screen alongside you speaking in a shared box, but I wasn&amp;rsquo;t particularly keen on that. My perfectionist tendencies kicked in here and I decided to try my hand at video editing, so that I could edit out my mistakes and edit together the video stream with my face in it and the video stream showing the shared screen. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://shotcut.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;shotcut&lt;/a&gt; which is free and also relatively straightforward once you get the hang of it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Providing Valuable Feedback Online</title>
      <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/giving-feedback-online/giving-feedback-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/giving-feedback-online/giving-feedback-online/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/student-reflection-for-feedback/&#34;&gt;last post&lt;/a&gt; I was thinking about how to get useful feedback from students by asking them to reflect on their learning once a week. This week I&amp;rsquo;m going to make a note on the mechanisms that I have put in place for students to get feedback on their own work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trickiest part of this for me has been trying to balance giving valuable and insightful feedback with maintaining a reasonable work load. Initially I had thought about asking students to submit an assignment each week that I would mark and give back to them, but it was pointed out by one of my colleagues that this would be a lot of work for me each week. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to find something that falls somewhere in the middle of that balance, with a mixture of opportunities for automated feedback and more personalised feedback, as well as assessment being provided in multiple different forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/02602938.2012.691462?casa_token=dC_YZ5qUeTcAAAAA%3AxwI4kl-TEUpXwNiKxAxMDatzSqVBrgT_7DfWEUXTltJqBDkMP0W1JMpdey0zj4BBsKR7J8OSJZeQ&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This article&lt;/a&gt; highlights the importance of allowing students space to reflect on their learning (which I&amp;rsquo;m doing), as well as providing various mechanisms for feedback. With that in mind I am proposing three main broad opportunities for feedback which I&amp;rsquo;ve described below. Each of these broad categories will have multiple activity types associated with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;weekly-qa-forums--email&#34;&gt;Weekly Q&amp;amp;A Forums &amp;amp; Email&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m planning on highlighting the forums and e-mail correspondence as opportunities for feedback this year. In my experience (and from speaking to some of my colleagues) students often think of feedback as being comments on a submitted piece of work, rather than responses to questions about their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want these activites (although primarily the Q&amp;amp;A forums) to be seen as a mechanism for feedback as well as a study resource. I think that this may help to encourage the students to participate in the Q&amp;amp;A forum. I also want to encourage students to participate in these by answering each others questions, although I am less optimistic about this, based on my own experiences and those of my colleagues. I want to do some further reading on the subject, so watch this space for a blog post about using forums in online learning!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;activities-built-into-content&#34;&gt;Activities Built into Content&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have chosen to structure my material in a &amp;ldquo;see one do one&amp;rdquo; format, where the students will be given some information and will then be given a related task to do. The plan is that these will take the form of multiple choice quizzes, interactive elements powered by either 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://shiny.rstudio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shiny&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://h5p.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;H5P&lt;/a&gt; or an interactive programming exercise. I currently use Datacamp Lite, but am hoping to transition to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rstudio.github.io/learnr/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;learnr tutorials&lt;/a&gt;&amp;hellip;I&amp;rsquo;m just waiting on the neccesary infrastructure to be in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within these elements, I want to make the feedback as valuable as possible. With that in mind it is key that the students get more than just whether their answer was right or wrong. the programming exercises allow you to build this in and direct the student to where they should consider changing their code, and allows me to incorporate feedback to encourage best practice in programming. Similarly it is straightforward to incorporate valuable feedback into multiple choice questions by correcting the reasoning that would lead to a student selecting each wrong answer. This is something that should be considered when designing the questions. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cft.vanderbilt.edu/guides-sub-pages/writing-good-multiple-choice-test-questions/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;This guide is pretty useful&lt;/a&gt; although constructing appropriate alternatives will be very context specific. H5P will be treated similarly to quizzes but will be more appealing and will add some more variety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Shiny applications are more challenging. With these, the idea is to build the feedback into the app responses, so that students can see the results of changing different parameters (and hopefully come to their own conclusions). This type of feedback is less &amp;ldquo;in your face&amp;rdquo;, but still very useful from an 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.wellesley.edu/sites/default/files/assets/departments/pltc/files/faculty/lewis_williams_1994_experiential-learning-past-and-present.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;experiential learning&lt;/a&gt; point of view. These apps will be combined with other activities (e.g. programming exercises or discussion forums), though these will depend on the specific learning outcome that is associated with the activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that the feedback provided by all of these will be useful for sparking discussion, both during live sessions and within the Q&amp;amp;A forums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;weekly-formative-assessment&#34;&gt;Weekly Formative Assessment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m also building a weekly assessment into the course. These won&amp;rsquo;t contribute to the final mark, since any changes to the assessment would need to be approved. Given the number of other changes that I&amp;rsquo;m making right now, I felt that going through the process to add these quizzes into the summative assessment would be too much. If these are successful then I may consider incorporating these into the course assessment in the future. Nevertheless, these are being planned to provide the students with additional feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These assessments will be a mixture of quizzes and submissions. The quizzes would cover a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of materials and the submissions would be more involved and would cover more materials. I am aiming to make the submission examples similar to what might be seen in the mid-semester class test.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help with giving feedback on the submissions, and in the interest of balancing workload and balance, I am currently looking into using rubrics a bit more. I have found 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.teachersfirst.com/lessons/rubrics/index.cfm&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this resource&lt;/a&gt; to be a really good guide so far. However, I am concerned that students may depend on having a  rubric for assignments and will focus on this rather than understanding course content. I had a scan through 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bearworks.missouristate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3981&amp;amp;context=theses&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this masters thesis&lt;/a&gt; which specifically focusses on the use of rubrics, and the literature seems to indicate that students like rubrics, and find them to be useful reflective tools. In addition to this it is suggested that the use of rubrics may help to relieve anxiety around teacher expectations of assignments. The more I have looked into using rubrics, the more I have realised that I need to learn about them. It seems that to be really effective the content of the rubrics has to be clearly and carefully planned&amp;hellip;another future blog post perhaps! I think, if done properly, the short term effort will be worth it in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am planning to use these formative assessments as a mechanism for feedback from the students to me. This will help me to assess the impact of the feedback exercises that are contained within activities earlier in the week. It will also, when combined with the activities embedded within the course material and the weekly reflections, give me an overview of the particular sticking points that students are coming across and will help me to address these in a useful way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting Feedback from Student Reflection</title>
      <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/student-reflection-for-feedback/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/student-reflection-for-feedback/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In my quest to provide a happy and helpful virtual classroom, I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been thinking a lot about feedback. I know that it is important for me to give students timely and useful feedback, and I&amp;rsquo;m building that in to various aspects of the class. I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been focussed on getting useful feedback from students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I remember being an undergrad student and being asked at the end of a course to fill out a feedback form. I also remember finding that really annoying because I don&amp;rsquo;t get to see the benefit of any of that feedback. I wanted to make the effort to change things that students needed help with as the course progressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my regression class last year I tried to collect more feedback, and asked students to fill in a short (four questions) questionnaire each week online. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t particularly successful - out of a class of around 200 I would get around 10 responses each week. However, I will say that the responses the I did get helped me to either make useful changes to the course material (e.g. adding video content or additional exercises where people highlighted issues) or to address why I was teaching things in a particular way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m planning on still seeking weekly feedback, but I want this feedback to feel more student centred and I want to encourage students to reflect on how they feel about the course material. Student self-reflection has been indicated to help students see links in their studies, and take more responsibility for their learning (see 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jisc.ac.uk/guides/transforming-assessment-and-feedback/self-reflection#:~:text=Why%20is%20student%20self%20reflection%20important%3F&amp;amp;text=Research%20shows%20that%20a%20combination,time%2Dconsuming%20appeals%20and%20complaints.&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ascd.org/publications/books/108008/chapters/Learning-Through-Reflection.aspx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/42923742?seq=6#metadata_info_tab_contents&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ1146193&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a few examples). In the feedback, I want to focus on their own self-perception and their perceptions about the material rather than my performance, again trying to encourage the students to think about themselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;feedback-structure&#34;&gt;Feedback Structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve used the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.moodle.org/39/en/Feedback_activity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;feedback module&lt;/a&gt; in moodle to collect responses. The responses will be anonymous, and the questions will be split into two sections; one part that I won&amp;rsquo;t look at in detail, another that I will look at in detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-1-reflection-on-effort-and-understanding&#34;&gt;Part 1: Reflection on Effort and Understanding&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first section, which I only plan on looking at over the class as a whole, asks the students to reflect on how much effort they have put in over the week and how they would rate their understanding. I&amp;rsquo;m hoping that the anonymity of the feedback module will encourage students to think honestly about this, which will therefore drive some level of student responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This first part consists of two multiple choice questions as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./effort_understanding.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the first question, it is relevant to note that I&amp;rsquo;ve designed the online materials to take somewhere between 6 and 8 hours, to keep it roughly in line with the 6 hours of contact time that they would get if they were taking the class face-to-face. The course is a 20 credit model spread over 10 weeks, so in theory the students would be expected to spend 20 hours per week on the class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since this course is aimed at MSc students, I&amp;rsquo;m not particularly concerned with individual time management, but would be interested to see how much time students spend on the materials overall. I may reconsider this when I modify this course for the second year undergraduates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second question is about the student reflecting on their own understanding. I&amp;rsquo;m asking students to use this as a reflection tool and this isn&amp;rsquo;t something that I&amp;rsquo;ll look into beyond the overall class level. I&amp;rsquo;m also considering adding my contact details to this question to encourage students who would place their understanding in the bottom three categories to contact me to arrange a meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;part-2-reflection-on-the-materials&#34;&gt;Part 2: Reflection on the Materials&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second section will ask the students to reflect on the materials. There will be four questions (technically one is a sub-question) which allow the students to identify areas that they would like more information, areas that they felt were good and areas where they feel that some improvement could be made. These can be seen below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./Materials.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have tried to be careful with the wording of these questions, so that they take me out of the equation and put the ownership onto the students and what they want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first two questions are grouped together, and identify the concepts that students want more information about. This allows the students to identify areas where they need to focus their energy, and will also give me the opportunity to update materials where indicated by several students, or add information to the Q&amp;amp;A thread discussed 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/first-step-to-blended/first-step-to-blended/&#34;&gt;in my previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question asks students to identify activities that they have found most useful. This will encourage the students to think about what they have found more straightforward. By asking &amp;ldquo;Why?&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m trying to encourage information about specifically what is good. I can then use this information to enrich other activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final question asks students about what acitivites could be (should be?) improved. This will (I hope) help students to identify sticking points in the materials, and will help them to develop an understanding of how they learn best. I am trying to ellicit a bit more information by asking what they would change about the activity. This information, again will be valuable in helping me to identify things in each activity that I should by trying to avoid doing (and potentially replace these aspects with ideas from the previous question.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;other-aspects-of-feedback&#34;&gt;Other Aspects of Feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already mentioned that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t particularly interested in using this to look at individual student performance or engagement. I&amp;rsquo;ve implemented some more automatic tools for this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;student-performance&#34;&gt;Student Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the class I&amp;rsquo;m implementing a weekly quiz, which will cover all aspects of the materials from the week. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on using a mixture of question types, including open ended questions that I&amp;rsquo;ll mark and provide feedback on. Within questions that allow automated feedback I&amp;rsquo;ll provide detailed and specific feedback. I also want to encourage students to reach out if they are unsure of where they have gone wrong, or if their quiz mark is not what they had expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be able to use this to identify students who need additional support, so that I can try to encourage these students to ask for help.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;student-engagement&#34;&gt;Student Engagement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is always a bit more difficult to measure student engagement. How do you know if a student has actually watched a video or read some text? (spoiler: you don&amp;rsquo;t really.) Moodle contains the option to add a completion progress block to your class page (note that the completion block shown below is from a class with two weeks&amp;rsquo; worth of activities).&lt;/p&gt;





  











&lt;figure &gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/completion_tracking.jpg&#34; &gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://kate-pyper.github.io/img/completion_tracking.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;



&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each block corresponds to an activity, and will turn yellow for partially completed activities and green for completed activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I plan on using this, along with sensibly defined parameters for completion tracking in each activity to monitor student engagement (e.g. completed lesson or require a page to be viewed). Since I&amp;rsquo;m only trying to get a general overview of student completion this is sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Initial Step Towards a Blended Classroom</title>
      <link>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/first-step-to-blended/first-step-to-blended/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kate-pyper.github.io/post/first-step-to-blended/first-step-to-blended/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first ever blog post. I decided to start a blog to give me a place to write down some thoughts on my teaching, particularly as we head into a unique year thanks to Covid!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m doing a PGCert in learning and teaching in higher education and have now taken 40 credits worth of classes. I&amp;rsquo;m really interested in the different teaching and learning pedagogies and wanted to try something totally new. Specifically I&amp;rsquo;m keen to implement blended learning in my classes, which isn&amp;rsquo;t currently the norm in my department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I&amp;rsquo;ve learned anything from my PGCert so far it&amp;rsquo;s that reflecting on teaching practice is really important. For context, I&amp;rsquo;ve taken over a class for the next academic year that has been in its current state since its creation (around 10 years ago I think) and I&amp;rsquo;m keen to make some fairly big changes to it. I&amp;rsquo;m definitely expecting some challenges to pop up along the way and wanted to have a dedicated space to keep track of the changes that I&amp;rsquo;ve made, along with my successes and failures. If anyone happens to come across this and have a bit of discussion around anything then that&amp;rsquo;s definitely a bonus!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;context&#34;&gt;Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class that I&amp;rsquo;m focussing on (for now) is a 20 credit module that is delivered to students across three different MSc programmes. The students come from a wide range of backgrounds, so we have to assume no prior knowledge of programming or statistics. We assume a base level of high-school level maths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course itself combines an introduction to programming in R with introductory linear regression. Each of these topics sits within its own five week block. When delivered face-to-face there are 6 hours of live content per week split between lectures and practical sessions. In the first 5 weeks this is 2 hours of lectures and 4 hours of tutorials, for the second half the split of lectures to practicals is 4 hours to 2. The first thing that I am planning on doing is making this more consistent throughout the class, following the structure in the first half to make the focus of the class more practical. This change is also in line with the learning objective of the class, which focus more on the students being able to complete a full analysis (although of course the theoretical components will still be there!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The class will be based in Strathclyde&amp;rsquo;s VLE, MyPlace, which is a wrapper for Moodle. So most (but not all) of the things that I discuss here will relate to Moodle as well as MyPlace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;general-structure&#34;&gt;General structure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the course, each week will consist of two topics. The main learning materials that would be covered in lectures will be split into sensible small chunks, and each chunk will build on the previous chunk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These chunks will have some reading or video content to give students information, and will be associated with at least one exercise or quiz for feedback to provide deeper understanding. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.moodle.org/39/en/Lesson_activity&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;The lesson module&lt;/a&gt; in Moodle is an underrated feature that lends itself well to this, and external tools can be easily embedded into individual pages within the lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to pull materials from a variety of sources, including some that I&amp;rsquo;ve developed myself. I still have to work on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;tutorials&#34;&gt;Tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one thing that I have thought a lot about recently is how to deliver a typical computer lab or tutorial remotely. I think that, given that the students haven&amp;rsquo;t signed up to an online education, it is really important to still have synchronous sessions where students can interact with lecturers and tutors. Also important since it&amp;rsquo;s one of my favourite parts of teaching!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue with this is that not all students are comfortable with this, and some students may not even be able to access these session due to poor connectivity or limited technology. From my perspective then, it is important to think about a variety of options to provide tutorial support. I&amp;rsquo;ve decided on three main ways that I will provide tutorial support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Live tutorial session&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will function in effectively the same way as a regular tutorial, but will use Zoom instead of being in a computer lab. I&amp;rsquo;m planning on having multiple tutors (the exact number will be dictated by the class size) and splitting the students into breakout groups to encourage collaboration. The students will be given the opportunity to self-select their group prior to the semester starting. I&amp;rsquo;ll then make any adjustments to produce properly sized groups, and get feedback from students who are unable to attend these live sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tutorial sheets will be available, along with the other materials, the week prior (i.e. week 2 materials will be made available at the beginning of week 1) as is typical in our fully online classes. The only thing I can&amp;rsquo;t decide on is whether it is best to have a really structured session or a completely unstractured session. I can see pros and cons of both. At the moment I&amp;rsquo;m leaning towards an unstructured session (as in a computer lab), where the tutors and I will drop in to tutorial groups almost in the same way as walking around a tutorial and talking to students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solutions for each tutorial sheet will be made available after the corresponding live session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Live &amp;ldquo;Office Hours&amp;rdquo; session&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second option for tutorial support is to attend a live drop-in session. I&amp;rsquo;ll sit on an open Zoom session for an hour and answer any questions from students who drop in. The idea is that dropping in to ask a question will require less data (and less bandwidth) than a full live session, but still provides personal contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These sessions will be completely unstructured, and will require students to do the work and ask specific questions. The nice thing about this is that it allows screen sharing which makes it fairly straightforward to diagnose programming issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Discussion forum/email&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final way in which I will offer support is via a discussion forum. I haven&amp;rsquo;t had great success with these in the past, so I&amp;rsquo;m going to label these &amp;ldquo;Q&amp;amp;A&amp;rdquo; so that they have a definite purpose and students aren&amp;rsquo;t going to be put off by the word &amp;ldquo;discussion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If students still feel uncomfortable posting then I will answer questions via e-mail, and also add any relevant questions to the discussion forum with an answer. Similarly, if any common questions come up in the live tutorial or during the office hour session these will be added to the Q&amp;amp;A thread with an answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m anticipating that the forums will be populated by me for at least the first couple of weeks, but I&amp;rsquo;ll encourage students to look to these for answers and am hoping that seeing some questions that have already been asked will give students the confidence to post their own questions. These will then become a useful study tool, since they will essentially act as a &amp;ldquo;FAQ&amp;rdquo; for each week.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
